Can I send an email tonight?
I mean from your laptop?
You have an email account?
Of course not, I would
like to use yours.
Lasse?
Yes, Runa?
Why don't you want
to show me your poems?
You must have written hundreds
of them, since we met each other.
I already told you, I
am writing for myself.
Yes, but... I phoned one
of my friends this morning.
She knows someone who could
help you to publish your poems.
No, I don't want that! What I am writing,
I am writing for a different purpose.
What kind of purpose? To scrape
through life as a poor poet?
I am not one of these people who writes
to become famous and make big money.
So why are you writing so much?
Writing and poetry are
simply a part of me.
As well as travelling, I know.
You already mentioned that.
You know? I think you are quite strange.
Sometimes I get the impression that
you are living in a different world.
I don't expect you to understand
me! Not many people do...
I'm sorry! I didn't mean for
you to take it personally.
Alright. No problem.
So let's go...
The day is too beautiful
to spend it arguing.
Every day is too beautiful
to spend it arguing. Let's go!
Common Max, we are going! Common.
Are you ready, love?
No hurry, I paid you for whole night.
Of course.
Just don't think you'll get a penny back if you
are just gonna stare out of the window all night.
Sure. Let's talk a little.
Talk?
- Why not?
What kind of guy are you? Paying
all that money just to witter on?
Who said I only want to talk?
Fuck! I'm not into psychos!
I won't tell you my life-story and I am
warning you. Don't try to do anything stupid!
Alright.
So how about, I tell you something?
How about, I give you a
blowjob and you just fuck of?
You know, most of the
time I am a loser.
Just the very one who is standing
now right in front of you.
But sometimes it's different.
Then I'm someone special.
And my life makes sense. I'm someone!
So, who are you then?
I'm someone who helps
others in their misery.
Someone who delivers
them from their fate.
Someone who protects and liberates.
I'm...
- Who? Batman?
No-no-no...
You know what? It's not my
job to listen to this rubbish.
My job is to do something else...
Are you listening to me now?
You are sleeping... Maybe it's better.
You know...
I'm not only showing
the helpless their path.
I'm saving them!
Did you hear me? I'M SAVING THEM!!!
Shit... shit... Sick bastard!
Fuck of you fucking bitch!
For a long time now I've
been neglecting you...
But don't be too sad, for there
are no new adventures to report.
In fact the moment has come and
in peace my decision matured.
Finally I feel that the time of
travelling is coming to an end.
Now we will return home. Together.
And our eternal dream will come true.
I so appreciate the way you
have been waiting patiently.
We will meet again. At the usual place.
By the time the sun blessedly smiles for the
fourth time, our aspiration will be nursed.
Morning.
Hey...
Can I turn off the radio?
Strange ritual.
What do you mean by that?
Every day you ask me the same thing.
Just turn it off! I am
not even listening to it.
Didn't you sleep well? Or... you are
still angry because of yesterday...
I don't know.
What is it?
I've never seen this side of you.
What is it with you?
You have no idea how much
you mean to my brother!
What are you driving at?
You found the letter.
No! I mean I don't know
what you are talking about.
I am talking about that I
am going to say farewell...
to the two of you quite soon.
What does it mean, quite soon?
Within a few days.
In a few days. Of course!
It's not a problem, is it?
Go! Just leave! Go without warning
just like you came into our lives!
Why this anger, Runa?
Let us depart as friends.
You and Max will stay
in my heart. Always!
So that's it... You come into
my life, take what you need...
And then leave. Regardless
of the consequences.
Please don't be unfair. You were looking for
someone to help take care of your brother.
And I've been there for him.
But now it's time for me to
move on. You will find someone.
How can you be so selfish?
I was hoping you would understand.
In this situation I think it's for the
best if I move on as soon as possible.
You should know better!
Magnus! Magnuus!
He robbed me of my sleep. Again!
That son of a bitch!
Same shit, different night.
You've been dreaming of father again.
Yes, about that bastard again!
He just won't let me live in peace!
Bastard!
He's to blame for all this.
Him! Never forget that!
Yeah, Yeah...
He got us into all this.
Always remember that!
Always!
No wonder you are dreaming about
him after getting out his pictures!
Like you always do when you are wasted!
Throw them away and be done with them!
Don't you tell me what to do!
The bastard simply abandoned me.
He destroyed everything!
He just disappeared...
He took the best from me...
And you are still here...
It doesn't make any sense at all.
Magnus! Magnus stay with me!
Don't leave me alone...
So you are leaving to another girl...
What makes you think that?
With all those women
listed in your address book.
No, I'm only moving on.
... to another girl.
Please, don't be unreasonable again!
I'm not good enough for you.
No! It's not about
that. You are wonderful.
But I have to move on.
I'll be in touch.
Do you really want to
let me and Max down?
Let you down??? I don't understand
what you are talking about.
You have everything you need.
Give that to Max from me.
This is Mr. Petri Smödhelm. So
far he's been everywhere with me.
He's almost become a part of me.
But when Max saw him, there
was this glint in his eye.
Petri will be in good hands with him.
Max doesn't need a doll. He needs you!
You mean a lot to him!
Please understand. I
have to go. I cannot stay!
Thank you for everything
from the bottom of my heart.
I'll be in touch.
I need you too...
Hello Lazarus...
Our date seems like a really bad movie.
What do you mean by that?
Don't get me wrong. I'm serious.
It's just so... absurd.
Yet it serves you.
- Please... Lazarus.
You don't have to
pretend anything to me.
It serves us both.
I mean... I just cannot understand...
Why you are doing this... There
must be some deeper reason behind it.
I just want to help.
Just help... Just help...
And how many have you
already 'just helped'?
Don't know... I'm not counting.
Is it okay with you if I smoke?
Yeah.
Thanks.
You know... All losers smoke.
But not all smokers are losers.
- Well...
And which group do you belong to?
You know... It seems I'm
a member of the first one.
Since my accident, a few years ago...
I've only been able to bear all
this by retreating into my dreams.
But at some point, at some point...
...it becomes clear that
it's just ridiculous.
It's fucking ridiculous to
simply jump from dream to dream.
Fucking shit...
Hey, let's go for a walk.
Yeah, exactly. Exactly! Go for a walk!
Good idea for Ari!
Good morning. Can I
speak to Lasse Ljandi?
Oh, there is no Lasse Ljandi. Thank you.
When did you make this decision?
You really want to hear about that?
At first, the only person who
made my life worth living left me.
A lost love...
No, Lazarus.
I know you probably hear these
kind of stories all the time. But...
with me it's different.
Somehow he didn't actually leave me.
He just wasn't around
often enough for it...
... to be like that.
He stopped feeding my dreams.
However.
A few days ago I found out that my
biggest wish will never come true.
So right now... Nothing
makes sense anymore.
Maybe even this doesn't
make sense anymore...
What you are doing is right.
You even mentioned that
it can't go on like this.
Yeah. You're probably right.
Trust me.
You promised it will be painless.
As promised.
Just one more thing Lazarus.
I've got something for
you. It's in my flat.
What is it?
My legacy. For you.
But you will see.
What is it?
Just take the keys.
You will find it in my
flat between the pictures.
What you are talking about?
You will see.
Promise that you are going to go.
I promise.
I'm ready then.
Drink this.
I'm with you.
Petri Smödhelm...
Hello? Is this orphanage Smödhelm?
You are not from here, are you?
No, I'm just visiting
for a couple of days.
And... whose guest are you?
Pastor Johansson.
Are you a relative?
No, just a good friend.
I got to know him in Gothenburg,
before he took up his position here.
Beautiful dog, isn't he?
Yes, truly a noble dog.
Well, he has cost me a fortune.
Life shouldn't be for sale!
I wouldn't have bought a dead dog.
But... Who knows... In some
countries they go straight to the pot
They eat dogs in China.
Have you ever been there?
Yes.
And... was it tasty?
China, China... quite far away.
Do you know someone there?
I've met many people and visited
many places during my journeys.
So, how long have you
been travelling around?
About 5 years. But every now
and then I return to Gothenburg.
So... probably... you experienced a lot.
Good things and bad things.
So maybe you can show me
some pictures of China.
I don't have any pictures.
You travelled that far and you
didn't even take any pictures?
Everything I experienced I wrote
down and I have it in my memory.
So you wrote a book?!
No... letters. To my
companion in Gothenburg.
He cannot travel himself. That is why
I let him share all my experiences.
Got ya.
And... Where are you heading next?
Home.
I mean first to Gothenburg.
To meet my companion.
So... I wish you good luck.
And next time, do not forget
to take some pictures for me.
Got ya?
Got ya.
Hello young lady. May I help you?
Is this orphanage Smödhelm?
- Yes.
I am looking for someone.
Where can I find help?
You have to go to our receptionist.
Linda Borg.
After entering the building,
it's the first door to the left.
Thank you.
Good luck!
Come in!
Hello. I have a small request
which I would like to ask you.
Please. Take a seat.
I came here from Halmstad because
I'm looking for an old friend.
Lasse Ljandi.
Yes... We have a file on a Lasse Ljandi.
So? What can you tell me?
I'm sorry. I'm not allowed to
give you details from our database.
Please! It really is important for me.
I really... I really cannot do it.
Can't you make an exception
in my case? Just this once?
I can assure you at least that there is no
current address in the file of Mr. Ljandi.
Thanks anyway...
Listen...
It's written in the file that Lasse
only had one close friend here.
Ari Kjelva.
Where can I find him?
Gothenburg. It's written here that he left
the orphanage and got a job in Gothenburg.
But I did not tell you that. Ok?
Hello?
Could you please open the door?
I have a message for your
neighbor Ari. Ari Kjelva.
Ehh, you'd better come straight
upstairs. Uppermost floor.
Why?
It's a long story.
Hi. What's with Mr. Kjelva?
He is.. Just come inside for a sec.
You want some coffee or a beer?
Thanks. Coffee would be nice.
Ok, Just a moment.
So where are you from?
Halmstad.
Do you want to visit Ari? I
haven't seen you around before.
Yeah.
You're sitting down. That's good.
Why?
What is the best way to explain it...
Explain what?
Well...
He's dead.
Dead? It can't be.
Well it can. Suicide.
Damn...
Little wonder. That
wasn't a life anymore.
He virtually never got
out of this house...
...and his only visitors were the supermarket
delivery service and the Pizza-guy.
You want a cigarette?
Thanks. Not now.
So... What did you want from Ari?
He has some information I need.
Really? What kind of information?
It's a private thing.
I see.
But there has to be
some way into his flat.
I will see what I can
do for you, Sweetheart.
The doors here aren't
so difficult to open.
Thanks.
Hey... easy, easy.
Let's wait till it's dark and all those
pensioners stop creeping around the staircase.
Can you do it?
I think so.
Somehow it looks exactly
like I expected...
The computer must have
been taken by the poli...
(How did he know my name?)
Who was that???
I have no idea!
Common. We'd better go.
Not before I've found something.
What if the guy comes back
or someone sees the light?
Ten minutes. Okay?
What is so important?
Found anything?
Hey. Little princess. Don't be sad.
Come on. Get up.
Nothing. Not even the smallest clue.
What were you looking...
Don't cry...
A glass of wine and the
whole world looks different.
So where have you been
prowling around again?
Probably boozing all night?!
Who do you think you are?
You'll never become anything!
It's none of your
business where I've been.
And how it's my business!
I'm still your mother.
Whatever. Want some coffee?
Don't change the subject!
You think I went through the torment of your
birth just to see you throwing your life away?
So far it hasn't bothered you!!!
It can't go on like this!
Not again.
You lazy bastard, you're becoming
too much like your father!
It's about time you went out and earned
some money and got me out of this hell!
Oh yeah! Great plan!
You've had it before!
YOU'VE HAD IT A THOUSAND TIMES BEFORE!
I don't give a shit about all this
here! I don't give a shit about you.
Leave me alone! Finish your
breakfast beer and shut up!
I beg your pardon?!
Don't talk to me like that.
After all I am your mother!
I'm the only thing you've got!
You want that you're
the only thing I have!
Since I was a child, you've tried to make me
dependent by letting me feel guilty about everything
Since I was a child, you've tried
to convince me that I'm a loser!
And yes, of course it's my fault
that you have to live like this!
OF COURSE!
Yes, it's your fault! YOU
and your BLOODY FATHER!
You've both ruined my life!
Yeah...
If you hadn't involved
yourself with this asshole...
If he hadn't fucked you...
We could both have one
big problem less right now!
What did I do? I deserve better!
You're so pathetic. Sitting here,
whining and boozing all the time.
No one is going to save you!
... I certainly not! Forget it!
How much such a small change of
perspective sometimes can give you...
Hello Lasse. How was your
journey to Gothenburg?
I'm sorry, do we know each other?
I'm a close friend of Ari.
Ari...? We wanted to go
together on a journey.
He is waiting for us there...
He was so impatient that he
left a couple of days ago.
That sounds strange...
Did something happen?
Well... I mean...
He stayed at home a lot. And didn't
have many visitors... you know.
He finally wanted to get going.
Did he say anything?
Only that I should meet you and
that you will show me the way.
He inaugurated you?
Yeah...
In that case we can
make our way together...
Good.
All right. Ari will have
done the right thing...
And really soon we will be reunited.
That's true. Shall we go?
Yes, our train leaves soon.
Why are you looking stupidly at me?
You parasite!
Sod it. Just leave me alone!
Now you're telling me what to
do? No one tells me what to do!
Least of all someone like you!
So you must be something better?
You can bet your life on it!
What is happening here?
Nothing!
But you have been pestering him...
Yeah... just a little
difference of opinion.
Thanks for the ticket.
What was worth getting
in such a rage about?
Just had to let off some steam.
You should try it sometime.
Somehow I get the feeling you need it.
What I'm interested
in Magnus, is this...
How did Ari set off for the Inarijärvi?
He went with a woman... by car.
A woman?
Yeah, they got to know each
other in some on-line chat.
It seems in my absence more happened
than I ever could have anticipated.
I am glad for Ari, that he found
someone he thinks is worthy.
Apart from you of course.
Yeah, they seemed to be quite happy.
He must have changed a lot...
But what I don't understand...
that he inaugurated so many.
Actually we wanted to go this
way alone. Only the two of us.
He was just waiting until
I was prepared for it.
Now you are prepared...
Yes... my years of travel are over.
I've seen the world, like
I was instructed to...
I've learnt enough about the
people in it and I found myself.
My decision is made.
I want to settle down at the Inarijärvi.
With my family and those whose
spirits share the same values as me.
At the Inarijärvi... Northern Finland...
Isn't that almost at the end of the
world? What is so special about this place?
Ari really did not tell you?
Even though he chose you...
No...
He only told me that I am worthy...
And that... I am to go.
I shall follow I mean.
With you.
He really did not tell you any more?
No, he only told me that you
will explain everything to me.
Our destination is
Valkaama... a poetic community.
It is situated far away from the hectic rush of
civilisation and all its sinister spin-offs...
A world without distrust,
envy and hatred...
... but full of pleasure,
full of love and security.
The inhabitants of this blessed
village have their own culture...
A culture, which is based on harmony
among themselves and vicinity of nature...
What now?
Tomorrow we are travelling
further towards the Inarijärvi.
By bus!
So let's go shopping then.
A very good idea. There
is still a long way to go.
Each to his own.
So what now?
We are looking for a quiet place
to eat and to spend the night.
Somehow everything is
different from in my dreams...
Well I think it's wonderful.
If I only consider... that just yesterday
I was in crappy Gothenburg... and now here.
When I was talking about the destination
of our journey a short while ago...
Did you really share
the same desire as me?
What are you getting at?
Do you think it doesn't mean
as much to me as it does to you?
Good heavens, no.
After all you are a chosen one.
You have been selected by Ari...
And in his choice I put my faith.
You know Lasse... If everything
is the way you said...
... it's probably the best
thing that could happen to me.
A real clean slate.
Are you not satisfied
with your past life?
I'd rather you didn't remind me of it.
It seems to me as if only
yesterday I was another person...
Don't you want to tell me more?
Better not...
Everyone has his dark secrets...
This journey is also
based on mutual trust.
Still I sense that our spirits are closer
to each other than I previously thought.
I just need time to figure you out.
What exactly is our destination?
South-East of Inari...
Along the shores of the Inarijärvi.
There will be signs to
show us the right way...
Are you tired?
Not really.
I'm really tired...
Hello.
Hey relax. It's just
a change of scenery.
I'm not fond of such places.
It's precisely why we are
finally going on this journey...
... to leave such things behind.
I know. But let us
celebrate one last time...
You mean drink?
Call it like you want.
That is nothing for me...
Well... If you want to
celebrate once again, do it then.
One last time...
In that case I would rather go for a walk
to savour the evening in a different way...
Okay...
So where shall we meet?
I will come along in a little while.
When?
In 2, 3 hours...
What do you want?
Can I sit there?
Closed community.
You don't seem to be a local?!
No, I am from Gothenburg...
And you are quite sweet.
Well, at least you're honest.
Just quite ill-bred.
Come on, just piss off!
Marie! What's the point?
Leave him!
Marie... beautiful name.
So, what brings you here Sweetheart?
Are you on holiday or are
you a criminal on the run?
Somehow we're all on the run, aren't we?
Stop babbling and just piss off.
Are those your lapdogs?
Believe me...
Go fuck yourself, it's good for stress.
Right, that's it!
Hey, stop it.
That your friend?
Fuck off! If I ever see your
face 'round here again...
Nothing would have happened to me.
I've got my Swedish Jesus with me.
Hey come on, Jesus!
Swedish Jesus... It was
a good one, wasn't it?
Even though I'm not a believer, it's
sacrilegious what you are saying.
Hey, it was a compliment!
Please, forget it! You are drunk.
We are going back to
our tent. Just leave it
(How could Ari give me such a person?)
Hey, I heard that, man! You think I'm
not good enough for you and your paradise?
Hey, I'm serious. You are
my Jesus! ... My Redeemer!
Ahh, you don't have a clue...
I'm sleepy... I just
want to go to sleep.
Andersson...
Kjelva...
Lasse!
Lasse!!!
LASSE!!!
Not at this time!
Hello?
Runa... it's me, Lasse
Lasse! My God! Where are you?
Are you two okay?
Yes of course! But where
are you calling from?
I'm in Gällivare.
What the hell are you doing there?
Runa...
Things are getting out of hand...
I almost don't have the strength
anymore to continue the journey...
I can pick you up! I will pick you up!
No distance is too far for me!
Gällivare is only a stopover. I
have to go on to the Inarijärvi.
Where do you want to go?
To Inari. In Finland.
Okay, so we'll meet there! I have to
see you again! When will you be there?
Probably today in the
evening... There is a church...
I have to go... I cannot
stay here any longer.
Lasse!
Damn...
International Bookings. My name is
Kristina Karlsson. How may I help you?
Hello, my name is Runa Eskleth. I need a flight
from Halmstad to Inari in Northern Finland.
Anna?
Could you take my
brother for a while again?
Yes, right now!
No! It's an emergency!
Lasse!!!
How did you get here...?
What happened? For Christ's sake.
I am so happy to see you again!
My whole world has fallen apart...
Just calm down first. What happened?
It's impossible to tell
you everything in brief...
At least have a try...
Come on, let's take a seat.
Ari is dead.
I know...
How do you know?
It... It's been in the newspaper.
I've been to Vänersborg.
I was searching for you.
I have also been to the orphanage.
Orphanage Smödhelm?
Yes... Where you were
abandoned by your parents.
No, that is not how it was...
I was supposed to stay there until my
father had established his community here...
Later on he sent me to see the world...
So I would appreciate his creation more...
Your father? ... What community?
I don't understand anything.
What's with your mother? Where is she?
Okay... let's look for a hotel
and tomorrow we will return to...
I can't go back, so close to Valkaama.
I have to return home to my father...
Okay... okay... Why don't
you tell me more about...?
About what?
Your father, the community,
Ari... everything.
I don't know where to start.
Just anywhere...
I had a companion on my journey...
Lasse! Wait!
I need a break.
We've already been walking for hours and
hours. Are you sure you know where it is?
Father said, along the western
shore and I will recognize the signs.
When was the last
time you talked to him?
It was years ago. We write letters.
I don't understand...
You don't have any fixed address...
so... where does he send them?
To Ari. I visited him once in a
while during my years of travel.
But you have never been here?
Lasse!
Yes?
Are you sure, you wanna
live here? In this community?
Of course.
And you and Max...
You two can also be part of
this idyllic and perfect world.
Just let's go.
Looks quite appealing...
Who is living here? In this solitude?
Maybe a hunter or fisherman...
Or someone who is crazy.
What about the bottles and the candles?
Maybe he wants to expel the
evil ghosts of the wood...
Of course!
No, I'm serious.
Many people who live in close
communion with nature are superstitious.
I often experienced this
during my journeys...
And you really wanna stay here?
And what if the owner of this stuff
returns? I wanna go back to the hotel...
Okay, just calm down...
We will spend here 4 hours... not more.
Only to sleep.
Common... please...
Two guests after all!
Anyway... I am Teemu.
So you are Lasse's father?
Is he here? My son
finally followed my call!
He is here. He is
looking for the community.
Where is the village? Is it close?
You are talking about the
community! Are you an initiate?
No... You are too weak to live in here.
What? What do you mean?
We live a hard life
full of sacrifice here...
A community of like-minded people...
Poetry every day and hard
struggle for survival.
And why can't I be a part of it?
You couldn't cope with the life here...
You are much much too
weak to survive in nature!
Oh! And Ari?
Ari was confined to a wheelchair!
How was he supposed to survive here?
Ari? He never wrote to
me about that! Even if...
He would never be one of us. He
would be unworthy of the community!
What kind of place is this? What kind
of pseudo-elitist-racists are you?
Watch your words! I don't have to justify
the community in the face of strangers...
This is a place of perfection!!!
A place of spiritual,
pure and elevated life!
But...
I have to move on...
They are waiting for me!
My son... Yes. My son has come!
I can track him here...
Why did you just leave???
I...
Don't you want to take me with you anymore?
Don't I have the right to a fresh start?
What did you do to Ari?
I accompanied him on his last journey.
No... Murderer!!!
Murderer? I helped
him! You deserted him!
I have been... I was...
Where?
With Runa.
With Runa?!
Amusing yourself with a woman?!
While Ari was sitting there in his dump... and
waiting to set off to a better world with you?
And now you are blaming
me for his suicide?
I have been writing...
It was already too late. He
was already devastated by then.
But together we wanted to...
This should all be different...
Yeah. It always turns out
different than expected.
I've met many people
who figured that out...
But this is my former
life... Where is Valkaama?
My son.
Father...
Father!
Father?!
Father? Noo. Nooo!!! You don't exist!
Father???
No... no... NO...!!!
He poisoned the community.
We don't want you here!
I will protect Valkaama!
You... you were in Ari's flat...
Welcome to paradise.
What now?
Don't know... Valkaama... Nothing.
We should leave.
And go? Where?
Home...
Yeah, you two go home.
What's with you?
I don't want to return.
Common...
Let's go.